6

Confrontation with Demons

In 1957 I left my pastorate in London, and Lydia and I went out to Kenya as educational missionaries. We became friends with a team of African evangelists who used to describe to us their personal encounters with demons.

On one occasion they were ministering to an uneducated African woman who spoke only her own tribal dialect. But the demon spoke out of the woman in English: “You can’t cast us out; you don’t have enough education.” To which my friends replied, “We’re not casting you out because we have education, but because we’re servants of the Lord Jesus Christ!”

I knew my friends well enough to be convinced that they were not exaggerating or fantasising. Their accounts of their dealings with demons reminded me of incidents recorded in the New Testament. But I did not know what to do with this information. Busy with my work as principal of a teacher training college, I put it in my “pending” file.

After serving for five years, Lydia and I left Kenya and travelled and ministered for two years in Europe, Britain, Canada and the United States. Then, in 1963, I accepted a position as pastor of a small Pentecostal congregation in Seattle.

One Saturday I received a phone call at home from Eric Watson, a charismatic Baptist pastor I knew slightly.

“I have a woman here,” he said, “who’s been baptised in the Holy Spirit. But she needs deliverance from evil spirits.”

I had never heard a Baptist pastor talk like that before. What followed was even more unexpected.

“The Lord has shown me that you and your wife are to be the instruments of her deliverance,” he continued. “And it’s to happen today.”

I was somewhat taken aback. I was certainly not prepared to let another person make such a decision for me. So I breathed a quick prayer: Lord, is this from You? Do You really want me to do what he says?

To my surprise I sensed the Lord respond, Yes, this is from Me.

“All right,” I said to the pastor. “Bring the woman over.”

The First Battle

While Lydia and I were waiting for Pastor Watson and the woman, we received a surprise visit from John and Sherry Faulkner, a Presbyterian couple who had recently been baptised in the Holy Spirit. We told them about the visitors we were expecting and invited them to stay and pray.

Then Eric Watson arrived with a fair-haired, blue-eyed woman he introduced as Mrs. Esther Henderson. I scanned her closely, looking for some outward evidence of her strange spiritual condition – a wild look in her eye, perhaps, or a metallic ring in her voice. But she seemed to be a perfectly ordinary, middle-class American housewife, somewhere in her middle thirties, I judged. She did not seem nervous or frightened.

Pastor Watson got down to business immediately. He sat Esther down in a chair and explained, “She’s been delivered from a demon of nicotine, but there are others.”

Listening to what he had to say, I decided to remain neutral until the Lord gave me some clarity or direction.

Pastor Watson stood in front of Esther and said in a loud voice, “You evil spirits, I command you to come out of Esther!”

When there was no obvious response, his voice grew louder and he repeated the same words: “I command you to come out!”

Still nothing happened.

“I know you are there,” the pastor continued, “and I command you to come out, in the name of Jesus!”

The moment he mentioned the name of Jesus, there was a definite reaction from Esther. As I watched closely, her countenance changed. It was as though another personality was coming to the surface. A yellow, sulphurous glow appeared in the centre of each eyeball. I knew there was another power inside this ordinary-looking Baptist housewife.

Eric Watson continued to stand and shout at whatever it was. Apparently he felt that shouting gave him more authority. But after a while, seeming to realise he was making no progress, he looked questioningly toward me.

I had been thinking it over, recalling especially the methods of Jesus. So I took my stand in front of Esther and said something like this: “Now, you evil spirit that’s in this woman, I’m talking to you and not to the woman. What is your name? In the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, I command you to answer me.”

The answer came immediately – just one syllable, uttered with incredible venom: “Hate!”

Everything in the woman’s face registered pure, undiluted hatred. Never in all my life had I seen such hatred in anybody’s eyes.

The promptness of the demon’s answer took me by surprise. I did not know what to do next. But I decided to follow the instructions Jesus had given His disciples.

“In the name of the Lord Jesus Christ,” I commanded, “you spirit of hate, come out of this woman.”

An insolent voice, not in the least like Esther’s, replied, “This is my house. I’ve lived here 35 years. And I’m not coming out.”

Unbidden, there came to my mind the Bible passage in which the unclean spirit that goes out of a man says, “I will return to my house from which I came” (Matthew 12:44). So the demon’s reference to Esther as “my house” was in line with Scripture.

With this in mind, I said to the demon, “In the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, you are coming out.”

The demon continued to defy me while I continued to say, “In the name of the Lord Jesus, you are coming out!”

It was a real conflict of wills. It seemed that I had to beat the demon down stage by stage. Each stage took quite a while. But the more I quoted Scripture and used the name of Jesus, the more I gained ascendancy over my enemy. Eventually the demon began to bargain with me. “If I come out,” it said, “I’ll come back.” I said, “No, you’ll come out and you’ll stay out.”

Then it said, “Well, even if I come out, my brothers are here and they’ll kill her.” I said, “No, you’ll come out first and your brothers will come out after you.” At the same time, I realised I had picked up a useful piece of information. Apparently there was more than one demon there.

Then the demon said, “Even if we come out of her, we’ve still got her daughter.” I said, “No, you’ll come out of Esther first and then you’ll come out of her daughter.” I had not known that Esther had a daughter, but I was following a simple principle: Whatever the demon said, I said the opposite.

At this point the demon changed its tactics. Without any warning Esther’s arms rose up and crossed over her throat, and she began to throttle herself with her own hands. Her face turned purple and her eyes began to protrude out of her head. John Faulkner, the Presbyterian, who was taller and heavier than I, joined me, and with our united strength we finally succeeded in pulling Esther’s hands away from her throat. Her strength was supernatural.

Then I returned to my battle with the demon. I began to feel a tremendous pressure inside my belly, like an inflated balloon, that seemed to be pushing against the demon in Esther. Suddenly a hissing sound came out of Esther’s mouth. Her head fell forward limply and her body relaxed. At the same time, the “balloon” inside me was deflated. I knew the demon had gone out.

Soon, however, Esther stiffened up again and the “balloon” inside me was reinflated. I realised I was in contact with one of what the demon had called its “brothers.”

I went through the same procedure with the next demon, which named itself as fear. After another battle, it, too, came out. Once again Esther relaxed and the “balloon” inside me was deflated. Becoming tired, I stepped back and one of the other people took over, following more or less the same procedure that I had established.

By the time the struggle ended, nearly everyone present had participated. In all, the session lasted about five hours.

After fear, the next demons that named themselves and came out were pride, jealousy and self-pity. So self-pity can be a demon! I said to myself. I was beginning to understand why some people could never seem to keep a positive, scriptural attitude during difficult circumstances. In fact, this whole process was opening up a new window through which I would henceforth view people’s behaviour and the forces that motivated them.

The next demon that named itself and came out was infidelity. I understood this as a spiritual force that sought to drive a married woman – and perhaps a married man also – to sexual immorality.

The next demon that named itself was death. At first I was sceptical. I had always regarded death as a purely physical condition. Then I recalled the horse in Revelation 6 whose rider was named Death. So death could be a person! Did that mean it could be a demon, too?

Intrigued, I said to this spirit of death, “When did you enter this woman?”

“About three and a half years ago,” it replied, “when she nearly died on the operating table.”

When the spirit of death finally came out, Esther was stretched on her back on the floor. Her skin was waxy and cold, her face like a death mask. There was no hint of colour anywhere in it. Anyone walking into the living room at that moment would have concluded that there was a dead woman on the floor.

I recalled the incident after Jesus had delivered a boy from a deaf and dumb spirit, and the boy “became as one dead, so that many said, ‘He is dead.’ But Jesus took him by the hand and lifted him up, and he arose” (Mark 9:26-27).

Esther lay there for about ten minutes, then raised her hands and began to praise the Lord and speak in tongues. Finally, her strength beginning to return, she stood up. After about half an hour, we handed her over to Pastor Watson, who put her into his car and drove her home.

Lydia and I went back into our house where the Faulkners were waiting. We all looked at one another in amazement. Then someone said, “Let’s have a cup of tea!”

As we talked it over, we were all excited. For the first time we had seen a dramatic, objective, supernatural demonstration of the authority Jesus had given us over demons.

Another Captive Set Free

About halfway through the following week, Esther Henderson phoned my wife and said, “I think they’re trying to come back. Could you come out and help me?”

We drove out to Esther’s home to counsel and pray with her. It seemed that the demons were oppressing her with fear, seeking to use that as a door of re-entry. We encouraged her to take her stand on the words of James 4:7: “Submit to God. Resist the devil and he will flee from you.”

While we were there, Esther’s youngest child, a little girl of six, lingered in the background. Rose was a thin, unhappy, withdrawn child. Each time I looked her in the face, she averted her eyes and bent her head down. She was, I learned, considered retarded.

Eventually I said to Esther, “I know the devil can’t be trusted to speak the truth, but when those demons said they had your daughter, I believe they must have been speaking the truth.”

“Would you pray for her?” Esther replied.

So Lydia and I made an appointment for her to bring Rose to our home for prayer the following Saturday. Then we invited the Faulkners to come and support us in prayer.

That Saturday, before we began to pray in our living room, I asked Esther how much she remembered of what had happened to her the previous Saturday. She remembered nothing, she said, from the time the demon of hate took over until she found herself lying on her back on the floor, praising God. The demons had completely submerged her personality and used her voice and features as channels through which they could express themselves. Esther also confirmed, when we asked her, that she had undergone a serious operation three and a half years previously and had nearly died on the operating table.

Now, when we began to pray for Rose, we followed much the same procedure as we had with Esther. Demons manifested themselves once again and took control of Rose’s countenance and features. They also spoke through the child’s lips.

I turned to Esther at one point and said, “Is that your daughter’s voice?”

Bewildered, she replied, “It isn’t even like my daughter’s voice. I never expected anything like this.”

Some of the demons in Rose had the same names as those in her mother, but there were not so many. As with Esther, the first one to manifest itself was hate, and the last was death. When death came out, Rose was stretched out on the floor looking like a corpse, just as her mother had been.

Once Esther and Rose were fully delivered, it seemed right to commit them to Pastor Eric Watson for ongoing spiritual oversight. I did maintain contact with Esther, however, for the next two years. During that time she apparently made good spiritual progress, although from time to time she still had to fight off demonic attacks.

As for Rose, she was transformed into a normal, happy little girl who was no longer considered retarded. The demons, it seemed, had been suppressing her natural personality and intelligence.

These experiences with Esther and Rose caused me to look at my congregation in a new light. I saw traits and forces at work in them that I had never understood. Could it be that they, too, had demons at work within them? If it was true of a “good” Baptist like Esther, could it also apply to “good” Pentecostals?

7

Challenged in My Own Pulpit

My congregation were good Pentecostals and I loved them. They sometimes testified, as Pentecostals are trained to do, of the peace and joy they enjoyed as Christians. I did not doubt their sincerity. But I also knew that at times their claims to peace and joy were a religious façade. Behind it were unrelieved tensions and pressures, which they did their best to suppress or conceal but which they never really overcame.

I began to preach about deliverance in a roundabout way. I suggested that perhaps some personal problems that were never fully resolved might be due to demonic activity. But my hints had little effect. My people sat back with indulgent smiles. “Our pastor’s got a bee in his bonnet,” they seemed to be saying, “but he’ll get over it.”

Left to myself, I do not know how I would have resolved this issue. But I was not left to myself. One Sunday morning, about a month after we ministered to Esther and Rose Henderson, both God and Satan intervened unexpectedly and shattered the superficial calm.

That morning I had chosen as my text part of Isaiah 59:19: “When the enemy comes in like a flood, the Spirit of the Lord will lift up a standard against him.” Although I was not aware of it at the time, I discovered later that one of my members had been recording the service on a reel-to-reel recorder. Listening to the tape later, I was able to evaluate objectively the content of my message, as well as the events that followed.

After I had been speaking for about fifteen minutes, the Holy Spirit took control of me, and I started saying things I had not planned to say. Even the pitch of my voice changed. I became unusually bold.

The theme of my message was: No matter what the devil does, God always has the last word. God began to bring examples to my mind.

“Egypt had their magicians,” I said, “but God had His Moses. Baal had his prophets, but God had His Elijah.”

Then the thought came to me that when God wanted to show Abraham what his descendants would be like, He took him out on a dark night, showed him the stars of heaven and said, “So shall thy seed be” (Genesis 15:5, kjv).

“We are the seed of Abraham by faith in Jesus Christ,” I said, “and we’re like the stars. When all the other lights are shining, you don’t see the stars. But when every other light has gone out, then the stars shine brighter than they have ever shone before. That’s how it is going to be at the close of this age. When every other light has gone out, we who are the seed of Abraham – through faith in Jesus Christ – are going to shine like the stars.”

When I spoke these words, a young woman seated alone on the front pew let out a prolonged, blood-curdling shriek, threw her arms into the air and slumped to the floor in a very unladylike posture. She lay there writhing and moaning right in front of my pulpit.

This was Satan’s challenge to my declaration that no matter what the devil does, God has the last word – a demonic manifestation directly in front of my pulpit! I had to either prove what I was preaching or stop preaching it.

At that moment I decided I would not back down before Satan. On the other hand, I felt I needed some support, so I called my wife, Lydia, forward. I knew I could count on her. Feeling I needed more reinforcement, I scanned the faces of my good, Pentecostal church members. They were all in a state of shock. Then, at the back, I saw our Presbyterian friends, the Faulkners, and called them forward.

The four of us gathered around the woman, whom I did not immediately recognise, as she lay writhing and moaning on the floor. Sherry Faulkner did not wait for a word from me. She was like a terrier after a rat.

“You spirit that’s in this woman,” she said, “what is your name?”

From the young woman’s throat came a harsh, gruff, masculine voice that said, “My name is . . .” But it would go no further.

Again Sherry asked her question, and the demon said, “My name is . . .” and stopped.

Each time she asked, she got the same response. So I stepped in and addressed the demon with the same formula I had used with Esther: “You spirit that’s in this woman, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, I’m speaking to you and not to the woman. What is your name?”

The demon responded again, “My name is . . .”

Each time I repeated the question, the response was the same. I found myself in the same, intense, person-to-person conflict I had experienced while ministering to Esther. But this time I had my congregation as an attentive audience!

I recalled that the disciples had reported to Jesus, “Lord, even the demons are subject to us in Your name” (Luke 10:17). So I said to the demon, “In the name of Jesus, you are subject to me. What is your name?”

Still the same answer: “My name is . . .” and no more. I saw that I had to beat the demon down with Scripture and the name of Jesus, and began to do so.

Suddenly the demon gave in. It shouted loudly, “My name is … lies!”

Everyone in the congregation went up into the air and came down on their seats with a bump!

I did a quick mental check with Scripture. In 1 Kings 22, I recalled, there was a lying spirit in the mouths of the prophets of Ahab. So the reply I had received was scriptural. And I got the impression somehow that this woman had been listening to lies rather than telling them.

I said to the demon, “You lying spirit, come out of this woman!”

The demon defied me; it refused to come out. But by this time I was confident that if I persisted in using the name of Jesus, it would have to obey me. Finally, after about ten minutes, the demon came out with a loud, sustained roar, like an express train going past. No human lungs could have sustained that volume of sound for so long. As the demon came out, the woman’s tongue protruded out of her mouth, bluish in colour and twisting like a snake. Then, as the roar subsided, she collapsed on the floor like an empty sack.

Standing there at the front of the sanctuary, I thanked the Lord quietly for my previous experience with demons in the privacy of my own home!

More to Follow!

It was evident that one demon had gone out of this young woman, but the pressure within me warned me that there were others still to be dealt with. Without this warning I could easily have said, “Praise the Lord, our sister has been delivered!” – and done no more. Sooner or later, however, her conduct would have revealed that she was not fully free, and the ministry of deliverance would have been discredited.

At the same time, I felt it would not be appropriate to continue the public ministry in the Sunday morning worship service. So I said to John Faulkner and the church treasurer, who was standing nearby, “If you will take this lady into my office, I’ll continue with my sermon.”

The two of them, along with Lydia, marched her off into my office while I returned to the pulpit. I found myself preaching to round eyes and open mouths. The morning’s demonstration had convinced them of the reality of demons far more effectively than any sermon!

After a little while, I heard dull thuds coming from the direction of my office. Then Lydia put her head around the corner.

“You’d better come in here quickly,” she said.

I knew she was not given to panic, so I said to the people, “I’ll close my sermon now, and you can either stay in the church and pray, or go home – whatever you feel like.”

Just as I left the platform, a member of the congregation, a godly woman who was the mother of the church pianist, walked up to me and said, “Mr. Prince, was that our daughter?”

I stopped in surprise. Sharon, our pianist, always sat in the front row. She was a solid Pentecostal, saved and baptised in the Holy Spirit since childhood. Her father was a Pentecostal pastor, her husband a Pentecostal Bible student and her brother-in-law a Pentecostal minister. She was a quiet young woman whose ministry was to play the piano, not in the least like the woman on the floor. I did not know how to answer.

Finally I said, “I think it must have been Sharon. There was no one else on that pew.”

“May I come with you to the office?”

“By all means.”

Sharon’s husband and father joined us, too, and we made our way together to the office. It was a scene such as I had never imagined. John Faulkner and the church treasurer each held one of Sharon’s arms, but whenever she could get a hand free, she was tearing off her clothes.

This is where preachers get into trouble! I thought to myself.

Aloud I said to Sharon’s husband and parents, “If you’d like to take Sharon to a psychiatrist, that’s perfectly all right with me. I will do nothing more unless you all assure me you want me to continue to handle this case.”

“We’d like you to handle it,” they all replied.

John Faulkner asked to be excused and left, followed by the treasurer, as Sharon’s husband and father took charge of holding her. As she came under their authority, the manifestations subsided.

Then Sharon’s mother drew me aside and began to tell me that she had been seeking an appointment for me to counsel with Sharon and her husband. This mother, a trained nurse, used discreet, professional language to describe what was happening between the young couple. In that decade Christians did not use the term oral sex, but I understood that was what she wanted to communicate.

I recalled the strange contortions of Sharon’s tongue as the lying spirit came out of her. Was that perhaps a manifestation of the demon’s activity?

As I began to talk to the family, another element came to light. Sharon had developed a strange infatuation with her brother-in-law – her husband’s brother – who was a minister. The two of them were exchanging letters that seemed harmless, yet could have sexual overtones. Sharon actually had one such letter, addressed to her brother-in-law, in her purse at that moment.

“That is a sinful relationship,” I said immediately, “and unless you repent and give it up, I cannot pray for you. You cannot expect Jesus to deliver you if you continue in this sin. But if you are willing to renounce it, then give me the letter that’s in your purse, and I’ll tear it up in front of you.”

It took ten minutes to convince Sharon. Finally she handed me the letter, and I tore it up and dropped it into the wastebasket.

As I put my hand on Sharon to pray for her, she slumped to the floor in a sitting posture, and I slipped down beside her. I felt the Lord showing me that there was only one position in which Sharon could receive deliverance: with her body pressed forward and her head between her knees. It was as if the Lord Himself was gently directing my movements. I put my hand on the small of Sharon’s back and pressed her body forward. Then I began to command the demons to come out.

For the next hour or more, they came out one by one, naming themselves as they did. Nearly all the names had a sexual connotation. One named itself as flirtation and another as petting. Some of the names were obscene.

Surprisingly, my hand on Sharon’s back served as some kind of electronic instrument. As each demon came out, I felt a gentle impact against the palm of my hand as if it were “registering” its departure.

When it seemed that the last demon had gone out, Sharon collapsed limply on her back on the floor and lay there for about ten minutes. Then she raised her arms in the air and began to praise God for her deliverance. As far as I could perceive, Sharon was fully delivered.

Yet the final outcome was sad. Sharon never came back to our church. She was too ashamed to be seen by the people who had witnessed her conduct that Sunday morning. To me, that seemed an indictment of our church. We were so “respectable” that people who were really in trouble would not come to us.

This led me to search my own soul. What was I pastoring? A middle-class social club that met on Sunday mornings? Or a place where people with real needs could come for help?

The decision I made determined my future. I could not in good conscience give the rest of my life to pastoring a middle-class social club. I decided I must devote the abilities God had given me to helping the people who most needed my help, even if it meant departing from accepted norms of religious behaviour.

But I had no idea what direction this decision would take me.

The Splash and the Ripples

The events of that Sunday morning were like a rock tossed into the middle of a pond. First there was a large splash, but then ripples moved out until they reached the margin of the pond. The splash took place when the demon cast Sharon to the floor in front of my pulpit. Within the next week, Lydia and I began to feel the effect of the ripples. People came to us from everywhere, most of whom we had never seen before. They came mostly to our home, not to the church. I have no idea how they found us, but week after week we counselled and prayed with people in our home for deliverance from demons. We seldom got to bed before two or three in the morning.

After a while my physical strength began to break down. I learned a serious lesson: If I do not care for my own physical and spiritual condition, I will not be in a state to help others get delivered. In fact, I might need help myself. I realised that a person who is worn down physically or spiritually is vulnerable to demonic attack.

I soon discovered, too, that proper instruction out of Scripture is essential for effective deliverance. (I will provide such instruction in chapters 21 and 22.) Before praying with people, I had to give them a sound biblical basis for what I was doing. In this way I built up faith in them to appropriate what Jesus had provided for them through His sacrificial death. Then, through our mutual faith, victory would be assured.

All this demanded many long hours. I realised I was in danger of neglecting my other pastoral duties. Was the time coming for me to resign my pastorate?

Meanwhile, God was leading me step by step from one new situation to another. Each successive situation revealed new aspects of the ministry – aspects I had to come to grips with. Then He led me on to the next situation – but only after I had “graduated” from the previous one. Evaluating all that had been happening, I realised God was not using the classroom method of a theological seminary to instruct me in the ministry of deliverance. He had me enrolled in a less prestigious school: the school of experience.

11

What Are Demons?

When people become aware of the reality of demons, two questions naturally arise: What kind of creatures are they? And what is their origin?

What Kind of Creatures?

I describe demons as disembodied spirit beings that have an intense craving to occupy physical bodies. Apparently their first choice is a human body; but rather than remain in a disembodied condition, they are willing to enter even the body of an animal (see Luke 8:32-33).

It is hard for us to entertain the idea of a person without a body. Nevertheless, even though demons have no bodies, they have all the normally accepted marks of personality:

Will
Emotion
Intellect
Self-awareness
Ability to speak

1. Will

The demon who has gone out of a man says, “I will return to my house from which I came” (Matthew 12:44). The demon here exercises its will to make a decision, and then follows it up with the corresponding action.

2. Emotion

“You believe that there is one God. You do well. Even the demons believe – and tremble!” (James 2:19). Trembling is an outward mark of strong emotion. As I have said, I have at times seen a demonized person, when confronted with the authority of Christ, begin to tremble violently. This may be an outward manifestation of the fear of the demon inside.

3. Intellect

Demons have knowledge not derived from natural sources. The first time Jesus confronted a demonized man in the synagogue in Capernaum, the demon spoke out of the man and said, “I know who You are – the Holy One of God!” (Mark 1:24). It was more than a year before Jesus’ own disciples began to realise what this demon had discerned immediately.

4. Self-Awareness

When Jesus asked the demonized man in the country of the Gadarenes, “What is your name?” a demon answered on behalf of itself and the other demons, “My name is Legion; for we are many” (Mark 5:9). The demon was aware of both its own identity and that of the other demons occupying this man.

5. Ability to Speak

In the first three gospels and also in Acts, we see several examples of demons able to speak through the vocal organs of the persons they were occupying. They could answer questions and carry on a conversation. Normally we regard the ability to speak as a distinctive mark of personality.

Now to the second question.

What Is Their Origin?

I have heard two main theories concerning the origin of demons.

They are some of the fallen angels associated with Satan in his rebellion against God.
They are disembodied spirits of a pre-Adamic race that perished under some judgement of God not recorded in detail in Scripture.

I do not believe that Scripture provides us with sufficient evidence to say with certainty which, if either, of these theories is correct. I must say, however, that on the basis of my experience, I find it hard to believe that demons are fallen angels. It seems clear to me that even fallen angels still maintain their dwelling place somewhere in “the heavenly places” (Ephesians 6:12) – although not “in the third heaven” where God dwells (2 Corinthians 12:2-4). It is not scriptural, therefore, to represent angels as operating continually on the plane of earth.

Demons, on the other hand, appear to be earthbound creatures.

Demons, as I have encountered them, display a wide range of character traits. Some are vicious, violent, supernaturally strong. Others are weak, cowering, even ridiculous – characteristics one would not expect to find in angels, even when they are fallen.

Let me illustrate from a particular case. A woman had asked me to cast the demons out of her husband. After I had prayed with him for a while, he showed signs of becoming violent. At this point his wife drew me aside and said, “At home he throws chairs at me.”

Why didn’t she tell me that before she asked me to pray for him? I said to myself, resolving not to get myself in such a situation again!

After a while, as I continued to pray for the man, what seemed to be the last demon spoke out from the man and said, “I’m unclean.”

Not wishing to ask questions and embarrass the man in front of his wife, I said simply, “You demon of unclean thoughts, come out of this man!” The rather vague phrase “unclean thoughts,” I felt, would not be too embarrassing.

The demon, however, responded, “That’s not my name.”

“Whether that’s your name or not, I don’t care,” I said. “I command you to come out in the name of Jesus!”

Eventually the demon came out of the man, but protesting to the last, “That’s not my name.”

My subjective opinion is that no angelic being, even a fallen angel, would behave that way.

Classical Greek literature may offer us some light on the nature of demons. The philosopher Socrates, for instance, acknowledged that he had a daimonion influencing some of his actions. This daimonion would never tell him positively what he should do, but would warn him negatively that he should not do certain things. One time, for example, a group of men were waiting for Socrates in the marketplace, planning to attack him. His daimonion warned him not to go to the marketplace that day.

In our terminology, we would probably classify that as the work of a divining spirit. It would be out of line with Greek thought, however, to suggest that Socrates had a fallen angel directing him.

I find it hard to believe that any angel would have the intense desire – which is characteristic of demons – to occupy a human body or, failing that, the body of an animal such as a pig. Surely, for an angel, that would be a place of confinement, not one through which such a being could express itself.

It is true that for the specific purpose of tempting Adam and Eve into rebellion, Satan did temporarily come to them in the form of a serpent. But subsequent passages of Scripture make it clear that he did not continue to occupy the body of a serpent.

Again in Luke 22:3-4 the writer records, “Then Satan entered Judas. . . . So he went his way and conferred with the chief priests and captains, how he might betray [Jesus] to them.” This does not necessarily indicate that Satan entered Judas in person.

Earlier the writer describes how Jesus healed a woman of a crippling back condition by casting “a spirit of infirmity” out of her (Luke 13:11). In commenting on this, Jesus described the woman as “a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan has bound . . . for eighteen years” (verse 16). The actual, immediate cause of the woman’s condition was “a spirit of infirmity.” But since this spirit was directed and controlled by Satan, its activity was attributed to Satan himself. Jesus said that Satan had “bound” her.

Similarly, in bringing about the betrayal of Jesus, Satan may have acted through some demon that he caused to enter Judas. (It might have been a spirit of covetousness, since Judas was apparently motivated by the love of money.) Alternatively, if Satan did enter Judas in person, it would have been similar to his temptation of Adam and Eve. His appearance to them as a serpent was a special action that lasted only a short while.

The fact remains that up to this present time, Satan’s headquarters and permanent residence are still in “the heavenlies.”

From the Heavenlies or Earthbound?

In chapter 2 I pointed out that the Greek word for demon (diamonion) is derived from a primary word, daimon. What, then, is a daimon?

Greek mythology, which is at best a fractured mirror, depicts two main orders of “gods” who dwell in the “heavenlies.” The higher is called theos (plural theoi). The lower order is called daimon.

One special function of the daimons was apparently to assign to each human being the destiny appointed for him by the theoi – the gods on the highest level. On a lower, earthly level are the daimonions (demons). They are dominated and directed by the “gods” on the higher level. Possibly the theoi direct the daimons, who in turn direct the daimonions.

It can be difficult for those who think only in English to form a clear picture of these three orders of spiritual beings, because English lacks the needed vocabulary. A theos is easily translated as a “god” and a daimonion as a “demon,” but there is no obvious English word for the intermediate category, a daimon. In this book I have chosen to use the transliterated form daimon.

It is possible that the two categories of theoi and daimons correspond to what Paul in Ephesians 6:12 calls “principalities and powers” [“rulers and authorities,” niv]. Both are apparently resident in “the heavenlies.”

On the other hand, the New Testament seems to picture daimonions (demons) as earthbound. There is no suggestion of their ever descending from, or ascending to, the heavenly regions.

In Matthew 12:43-44 Jesus gives a picture of the activity of a demon:

“Now when the unclean spirit goes out of a man, it passes through waterless places, seeking rest, and does not find it. Then it says, ‘I will return to my house from which I came’; and when it comes, it finds it unoccupied, swept and put in order.”

(nasb)

There is no suggestion that the demon either descends from, or ascends to, the heavenly regions. The Greek verb translated “passes through” is apparently used only of movement on the plane of earth.

Theoi, daimons and daimonions are united in a ceaseless war against the human race. Under Satan’s domination they work together to inflict on humanity every possible form of harm, deception and torment.

Let us suppose for a moment that daimonions are spirits that once occupied the bodies of members of some pre-Adamic race who led ungodly and sinful lives. In their present condition, however, they have no way to give expression to the various lusts and passions and emotions they developed in their former bodies. It is conceivable that they could find some kind of vicarious release by acting out their lusts or passions or emotions through human bodies. This would explain one dominant characteristic of demons: their intense craving to inhabit and work through human flesh.

We need to remember that the Bible records only the history of the race descended from Adam. In this connection it uses the phrase sons (or descendants) of Adam. It was to redeem the members of this race that Jesus came as “the last Adam” (1 Corinthians 15:45). If other races existed before Adam, the Bible makes no explicit reference to them. In his book Earth’s Earliest Ages (1876, reprinted by Kregel in 1975), G. H. Pember deals at length with this question.

I consider this theory of the origin of demons to be one possible hypothesis, but I am content not to pursue it further. There are some things God keeps secret (see Deuteronomy 29:29), and it is foolish to try to pry His secrets from Him.

It may be that neither of the two theories about demons is correct – that they are neither fallen angels nor disembodied spirits from an earlier race of beings. Our concept of demons, however, has a practical bearing on how we deal with them. I have confronted many demons of different kinds, but have never had the impression that I was dealing with angelic beings.

On the other hand, I have had a certain amount of contact with satanic angels through intercessory prayer and spiritual warfare, which could best be described in the words of Paul in Ephesians 6:12: “For we do not wrestle against flesh and blood, but against . . . the rulers of the darkness of this age, against spiritual hosts of wickedness in the heavenly places.”

The New Testament does not depict Jesus or His apostles as “wrestling” with demons. Rather, they confronted demons (as I said in chapter 3) and exercised the authority needed to expel them.

Demons in Scripture

Demons manifest themselves through humanity under many different names. The following is a list of specific names actually applied to demons in Scripture. Since translations vary in their use of names, I have given the name used in three translations, in the following order: the New King James Version, the New American Standard Bible and the New International Version. In each case the Scripture reference follows.

In the Old Testament

Jealousy/jealousy/feelings of jealousy: Numbers 5:14, 30

Ill will/evil/evil: Judges 9:23

Distressing/evil/evil: 1 Samuel 16:14-23; 18:10; 19:9

Lying/deceiving/lying: 1 Kings 22:22; 2 Chronicles 18:20-22

Perverse/distortion/dizziness: Isaiah 9:14

Deep sleep/deep sleep/deep sleep: Isaiah 29:10

Heaviness/fainting/despair: Isaiah 61:3

Harlotry/harlotry/prostitution: Hosea 4:12; 5:4

Unclean/unclean/impurity: Zechariah 13:2

In the New Testament

Mute/mute/robbed of speech: Mark 9:17

Deaf and dumb/deaf and dumb/deaf and mute: Mark 9:25

Infirmity/causing sickness/crippling: Luke 13:11

Divination/divination/predicting the future: Acts 16:16

Deceiving/deceitful/deceiving: 1 Timothy 4:1

Fear/timidity/timidity: 2 Timothy 1:7

Error/error/falsehood: 1 John 4:6

Other Demons

In addition to the names taken from Scripture and listed above, I will add some other names of demons that I have encountered personally.

In the Area of Physical Infirmity

Arthritis

Asthma

Cancer

Crippling

Epilepsy

Head pain

Migraine

Sinusitis

Thrombosis

In Other, More General Areas

Adultery

Claustrophobia

Criticism

Disappointment

Envy

Fantasy

Gossip

Hatred

Hopelessness

Masturbation

Murder

Perversion

Rebellion

Rejection

Religion

Self-pity

Stress

Suicide

Violence

Witchcraft

The lists given above are by no means exhaustive, but indicate the diversity of demonic activity. Satan apparently has at his disposal vast numbers of demons with which to assail and torment humanity.

Now we will go on to the second of our seven questions.